Finding Aid for Marston Bates Papers 1913-1974
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Correspondence
  - Alphabetical 1966-1970
    - Natural History Magazine-Fan Mail (Box 13)
      (13-18-13-20)
    - Natural History Magazine-Publisher (Box 13)
      (13-21)
    - O (Box 13)
      (13-22)
    - P (Box 13)
      (13-23)
    - Phi Beta Kappa (Box 13)
      (13-24)
    - Prentice-Hall, Inc. (Box 13)
      (13-25)
    - Q-R (Box 13)
      (13-26)
    - Random House (Box 13)
      (13-27)
    - Royalties-Miscellaneous (Box 13)
      (13-28)
    - Royalties-Prentice-Hall (Box 13)
      (13-29)
    - Royalties-Random House (Box 13)
      (13-30)
    - Royalties-Scribner's (Box 13)
      (13-31)
    - Royalties-Walker (Box 13)
      (13-32)
    - Russell & Volkenrig, Inc. (Box 14)
      (14-1)
    - S (Box 14)
      (14-2)
    - Sakharov and Wald (Box 14)
      (14-3)
    - Smithsonian (Box 14)
      (14-4)
    - Sociology (Box 14)
      (14-5)
    - T (Box 14)
      (14-6)
    - Television and Radio (Box 14)
      (14-7)
    - U-V (Box 14)
      (14-8)
    - Virginia (Box 14)
      (14-9)
    - W (Box 14)
      (14-10)
    - World Academy of Art & Science (Box 14)
      (14-11)
    - World Book (Box 14)
      (14-12)
    - X-Z (Box 14)
      (14-13)
- University of Michigan Career
  - Personnel/Committee Work
    - Bates Job Appointments 1935-1971 (Box 14)
      (14-14)
    - Bates Personnel Records (UM) (Box 14)
      (14-15)
    - Bates Instruction Records (UM) (Box 14)
      (14-16)
    - Student Government Council (UM) (Box 14)
      (14-17)
    - Student Quality, UM Committee on (Box 14)
      (14-18)
    - Student Relations, UM Committee on (Box 14)
      (14-19)
    - Students, Doctoral (Box 14)
      (14-20)
    - Systematic Biology, Committee on (Box 14)
      (14-21)
  - Lecture Materials
    (includes some outside lectures)
    - Zoology 38
      - Introduction Handouts (Box 14)
        (14-22)
      - Lecture Notes (I) (Box 14)
        (14-23)
      - Lecture Notes (II) (Box 14)
        (14-24)
      - Lecture Notes (III) (Box 14)
        (14-25)
      - Lecture Notes (IV) (Box 14)
        (14-26)
      - Lecture Notes (V) (Box 14)
        (14-27)
      - Lecture Notes (VI) (Box 14)
        (14-28)
      - Lecture Notes (VII & VIII) (Box 14)
        (14-29)
      - Lecture Notes (IX) (Box 14)
        (14-30)
      - Lecture Notes (X and miscellaneous) (Box 14)
        (14-31)
    - Zoology 111, Lecture Notes (Box 14)
      (14-32)
    - Zoology 142, Lecture Notes (Box 14)
      (14-33)
    - Zoology 298, Lecture Notes (Box 14)
      (14-34)
    - Zoology 303
      - Lecture Notes 1961-1962 (Box 14)
        (14-35)
      - Lecture Notes 1963-1964 (Box 14)
        (14-36)
      - Lecture Notes 1965-1967 (Box 14)
        (14-37)
      - Lecture Notes 1968-1969 (Box 14)
        (14-38)
    - Miscellaneous Zoology Exams (Box 15)
    - Lecture notes (outside engagements), 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Notebook containing miscellaneous lectures and writings on the "Human Environment" (Box 15)
- Journals diaries, research
  - Diary and reading records 1924-1928 (Box 15)
  - Journal, Letters and Reading Record 1928-1930 (Box 15)
  - Journal, Popol Vul 1930-1931 (Box 15)
  - Journal and Letters 1934-1935 (Box 15)
  - Journal 1935-1937 (Box 15)
  - Bates-Hackett Letters 1936-1938 (Box 15)
  - Research Reports, Albania 1936 (Box 15)
  - Research Reports, Albania 1937 (Box 15)
  - Research Reports, Albania 1938 (Box 16)
  - Research Reports on Larval Experiments 1938-1939 (Box 16)
  - Research Reports on Mosquitoes, Albania & Egypt 1939-1940 (Box 16)
  - Bates-Hackett Letters 1939-1943 (Box 16)
  - Journal & Research Reports, Colombia 1940-1941 (Box 16)
  - Diary & Reports, Colombia 1942 (Box 16)
  - Diary & Reports, Colombia 1943 (Box 16)
  - Diary & Reports, Colombia 1944 (Box 16)
  - Diary & Reports, Colombia 1945 (Box 16)
  - Diary & Reports, Colombia 1946 (Box 16)
  - Diary & Reports, Colombia 1947 (Box 16)
  - Diary & Reports, Colombia 1948 (Box 17)
  - Diary & Reports, Colombia 1948-1949 (Box 17)
  - Diary & Reports, Colombia 1950 (Box 17)
  - Diary, Ifalik 1953, 2 volumes (Box 17)
  - Field Reports, Ifalik 1953, 3 volumes (Box 17)
  - Notched cards (Ifalik Fauna) (Box 17)
  - Diary, Puerto Rico 1956-1957 (Box 17)
  - Diary, Jungle in the House, Ann Arbor 1964-1966 (Box 17)
- Writings
  - Book Manuscripts
    - Nature of Natural History 1950 (Box 18)
    - Prevalence of People 1955 (Box 18)
    - Ifaluk, Portrait of an Atoll 1958 (Box 18)
    - The Forest and the Sea 1960 (Box 18)
    - Man in Nature 1961 (Box 18)
    - Gluttons and Libertines 1968 (Box 18)
    - Jungle in the House 1970 (Box 18)
  - Reviews of Bates' Books
    - 1934-1972, 2 volumes (Box 18)
  - Articles by Marston Bates (Incomplete)
    - Index to Bates Publications, articles 4-18 (Box 19)
      (19-1)
    - Articles 18-33 (Box 19)
      (19-2)
    - Bound Articles 34-47 (Box 19)
      (19-2a)
    - Articles 39-69 (Box 19)
      (19-3)
    - Articles 70-82 (Box 19)
      (19-4)
    - Articles 84-98 (Box 19)
      (19-5)
    - Articles 100-110 (Box 19)
      (19-6)
    - Articles 112-121 (Box 19)
      (19-7)
    - Articles 122-126 (Box 19)
      (19-8)
    - Articles 128-133 (Box 19)
      (19-9)
    - Articles 134-140 (Box 19)
      (19-10)
    - Articles 141-159 (Box 19)
      (19-11)
    - Articles 161-167 (Box 19)
      (19-12)
    - Articles 168-173 (Box 19)
      (19-13)
    - Unpublished articles (Box 19)
      (19-14)
    - Unpublished articles (Box 19)
      (19-15)
    - Unpublished articles (Box 19)
      (19-16)
    - Unpublished articles (Box 19)
      (19-17)
    - Unpublished articles (Box 19)
      (19-18)
    - Unpublished articles (Box 19)
      (19-19)
  - Reviews of Bates' books
    - Gluttons and Libertines (Box 19)
    - Jungle in the House (Box 19)
    - Nature of Natural History (Box 19)
    - Natural History of Mosquitoes (Box 19)
    - Where Winter Never Comes (Box 19)
    - Darwin Reader (Box 20)
    - Man's Role in Changing the Face of the Earth (Box 20)
    - Ifaluk (Box 20)
    - Animal Worlds (Box 20)
    - Land & Wildlife of South America (Box 20)
    - Forest & Sea (Box 20)
    - Man in Nature (Box 20)
    - Prevalence of People (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous Scientific Publications, reprints, and newsletters (Box 20)
    - Miscellaneous topical files, including projected books, article ideas, TV scripts 1958 (Box 20)
- Notes/miscellaneous personal
  - Entomological and other scientific notes 1919-1932 (Box 21)
    (Colombia; Ifalik Atoll)
  - Faculty bibliography and biographical data (Box 21)
  - Marston Bates student compositions (Box 21)
  - Bates family clippings; include Marston Bates obituaries (Box 21)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series consists of photos taken during Bates's field work with the United Fruit Company in Central America, in Albania and in Colombia on mosquito control, and at Ifalik Atoll, Micronesia, on human ecology. There are also photos of Bates lecturing on television and family photos.
  - Numbered photographs 1929-1948
    - Log books, 3 volumes (Box 22)
    - Places
      - Albania 1936-1939
        - General (Box 22)
        - Laboratory (Box 22)
        - Larval habitat
          - No. 876-900 (Box 22)
          - No. 901-1000 (Box 22)
          - Nos. 1707-1823 (Box 22)
        - Mosquito techniques (Box 22)
      - Colombia 1940-1948
        - General
          - No. 1891-1900 (Box 22)
          - No. 1901-2000 (Box 22)
          - No. 2001-2100 (Box 22)
          - No. 2101-2200 (Box 22)
          - No. 2201-2300 (Box 22)
          - No. 2301-2400 (Box 22)
          - No. 2401-2465 (Box 22)
        - Hacienda Yurimena (Box 22)
        - Hacienda Yurimena Personal (Box 22)
          (Bates family)
        - Laboratory (Box 22)
        - Mammals
          - No. 1891-2100 (Box 22)
          - No. 2101-2465 (Box 22)
        - Mosquito habitat (Box 22)
        - Mosquitoes (Box 22)
      - Cuba 1932 (Box 22)
      - Egypt: Larval habitat 1939-1940 (Box 22)
      - Greece: Larval habitat 1937 (Box 22)
      - Guatemala 1929-1931
        (also includes Honduras)
        - No. 401-600 (Box 22)
        - No. 601-700 (Box 22)
        - No. 701-800 (Box 22)
        - No. 801-875 (Box 22)
        - No. 1001-1100 (Box 22)
        - No. 1101-1185 (Box 22)
      - Guatemala 1935 (Box 22)
      - Haiti 1934 (Box 22)
      - Honduras 1929-1931 (Box 22)
      - Honduras 1935 (Box 22)
        (See also Guatemala)
      - Hungary: Larval habitat 1937 (Box 22)
      - Massachusetts 1931 (Box 22)
      - Panama 1935 (Box 22)
    - Topics
      - Animals, 2 folders (Box 22)
      - Laboratories (Box 22)
      - People (Box 22)
      - Plants, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Numbered photographs, Ifalik 1953
    - General
      - No. 2501-2600 (Box 23)
      - No. 2601-2700 (Box 23)
      - No. 2701-2800 (Box 23)
      - No. 2801-2900 (Box 23)
      - No. 2901-3000 (Box 23)
      - No. 3001-3046 (Box 23)
      - Rolls LBA-LBE (Box 23)
      - Rolls LBF-LBK (Box 23)
    - Topics
      - Animals (Box 23)
      - Building (Box 23)
      - Canoes (Box 23)
      - Census (Box 23)
      - Children (Box 23)
      - Cultivation (Box 23)
      - Dance (Box 23)
      - Fishing (Box 23)
      - Food (Box 23)
      - Household areas (Box 23)
      - People (Box 23)
      - Shore (Box 23)
      - Vegetation (Box 23)
      - Vegetation-Species (Box 23)
      - Weaving (Box 23)
  - Numbered photographs 1964
    - Mexico trip and Ann Arbor (Box 23)
  - Unnumbered photographs
    - Field work
      - Places
        - Albania (Box 23)
        - Colombia, 2 folders color transparencies (Box 23)
        - Cuba (Box 23)
        - Guatemala (Box 23)
        - Haiti (Box 23)
        - Honduras (Box 23)
        - Ifalik
          - Air photos (Box 23)
          - Maps (Box 23)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 23)
        - Panama (Box 23)
      - Topics
        - People (Box 23)
        - Plants, animals, scientific apparatus (Box 23)
      - "Garden photos" (Ann Arbor)
        - Animals (Box 23)
        - Birds (Box 23)
        - Construction (Box 23)
        - Plants (Box 23)
        - Marston Bates and miscellaneous (Box 23)
    - Personal
      - Marston Bates as a child (Box 23)
      - Drawings of Bates by a student (Box 23)
      - Marston Bates family (Box 23)
      - Florida 1921-1922 (Box 23)
      - Marston Bates lecturing and on television (Box 23)
      - Life Magazine photos of MB (Box 23)
      - Portraits formal (Box 23)
      - Portraits informal (Box 23)
      - Marston Bates with others, groups (Box 23)
      - Slides (Box 23)
  - Negatives
    (Staff use only)
    - No. 501-1300 (Box 24)
    - No. 1501-2500 (Box 24)
    - No. 2501-3046 (Box 25)
    - Rolls LBA-LBK (Box 25)
    - Florida photos (Box 25)
Selective Index of Correspondents
Correspondence has been listed either by date and thus to be found within the chronological correspondence subseries, or within the alphabetical correspondence subseries (indicated by box and folder designation, e.g. 6-16)
Abbott, Donald Putnam.
4-20; 6-9; 6-10; 8-25; 10-7; 10-12; 12-16
Benitez, Jaime, 1908-
4-27; 6-13; 6-14; 10-17; 12-19
Boulding, Kenneth Ewart, 1910-
4-28
Brown, Dugald E. S., 1901-
4-28; 6-13; 8-4
Bugher, John Clifford, 1901-
March 1941-March 1943 throughout; also 6-14; 8-7
Burrows, Edwin G. (Edwin Grant), 1891-1958.
4-27; 4-28; 6-14; 6-16
Cain, Stanley Adair, 1902-
4-30; 9-4
Childe, V. Gordon (Vere Gordon), 1892-1957.
4-30
Crist, Raymond E.
3-25; 4-30; 6-17
Darlington, Philip Jackson, 1904-
July-December 1934 throughout; also Nov. 3, 1942, January 9, 1943 and letter in folder 4-17
DeVinney, Leland Collins, 1906-
4-33; 8-7
De Voto, Bernard Augustine, 1897-1955.
6-6; 6-7
Dice, Lee Raymond, 1887-1977.
4-33
Douglas, Paul Howard, 1892-
6-23
Dunn, Emmet Reid, 1894-1956.
August 29, 1943; see also folder 4-33
Ecological Society of America.
4-36; 6-24
Fairchild, David, 1869-1954.
March 11, 1928, March 15, 1931;May 15, 1931, October 9, 1934, November 20, 1934, .July 8, 1938, September 19, 1942, October 6, 1942, October 16, 1942, February 8, 1943, April 17, 1943, May 2, 1944, May 2, 1945, May 2, 1947, January 8, 1948, February 3, 1948, November 1, 1948.
Fairchild, G. B.
1-3; 1-6; 1-8; 1-40; 1-41; 1-42; 2-3; 2-4; 2-20; 2-22; 3-38; 3-39; 3-44; 4-1; 4-17.
Fairchild, Marian H.
August 24, 1911; September 1, 1941; December 27, 1941; May 11, 1944; June 7, 1945; February 15, 1948; February 18, 1948; see also folders 6-6; 6-7; 7-25
Fleming, R. W. (Robben Wright), 1916-
13-1
Gaige, Frederick M.
1926-May 1930 throughout; also October 25, 1935
Gerlach, Lee.
9-2; 9-17
Grosvenor, Gilbert Hovey, 1875-1966.
September 30, 1944; November 15, 1944; December 1948; see also folders 6-7; 11-25
Grosvenor, Melville Bell, 1901-1982.
November 17, 1947; November 24, 1947; December 9, 1947;December 18, 1947; December 22, 1947; June 1, 1948; July 26, 1948; July 30, 1948; August 3, 1948; see also folders 7-2; 7-14; 7-26.
Haber, William, 1899-1988
11-7
Hackett, Lewis Wendell, 1884-1962.
Letters for 1936-1943 in spring-back binders in box 15; April 1944-July 1948, throughout; also folders 5-5; 7-4; 9-18; 11-12
Hatcher, Harlan Henthorne, 1898-
5-4 (letter to Harlan Hatcher re the Markert investigation)
Hicks, Welmer K., 1909-
7-7
Hubbell, Theodore, 1897-1989.
1931 throughout; August 6, 1933; August 31, 1940, April 10, 1941; March 1, 1947; March 27, 1947; April 2, 1947.
John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation
7-2; 7-3; 9-17; 11-10; 11-11; 13-6
Just, Theodor Karl, 1904-1960.
5-8; 6-17
Kennedy, John S.
2-14; 2-15; 3-15; 3-16; 3-20; 3-34; 3-38; 3-39
Kinsey, Alfred Charles, 1894-1956.
July 12, 1933; July 20, 1933; August 11, 1933; see also folders 5-10; 6-7; 7-7; 9-4
Kumm, Henry William, 1901-
May 1943-June 1944 throughout, December 6, 1944; January 22, 1946; March 22, 1946
Logan, John A.
5-11; 7-8
Mead, Margaret, 1901-
4-20; 7-9
Muñoz Marín Luis, 1898-
7-9
Pollock, James Kerr, 1898-
5-21
Popenoe, Wilson, 1892-
1-8; 1-9; 1-14; 1-15; 1-16; 1-17; 1-18; 1-21; 1-22; 1-27; 1-28; 1-36; 1-38; 1-42; 2-1; 2-7; 2-15; 6-7
Rahn, Sheldon Lloyd, 1918-
7-23
Rockefeller, David, 1915-
2-11; 3-41; 6-17; 7-4; 7-5; 7-7; 7-11; 8-6; 8-7
Rogers, James Speed, 1891-1955.
1928-1929 throughbut; November 11, 1931; July 19, 1934; June 2, 1943; July 5, 1943; September 8, 1943; April 18, 1944; August 7, 1946; January 3, 1948; February 6, 1948; February 24, 1948; March 1, 1948; March 5, 1948; April 26, 1948; see also folders 5-25; 8-6
Rusk, Dean, 1909-
5-23; 8-6; 8-7
Russell, Diarmuid
5-26; 8-6; 8-8; 8-13; 10-5; 11-29; 13-4; 13-20; 14-1
Sauer, Carl Ortwin, 1889-
6-3; 6-7; 8-9; 8-21
Sawyer, Ralph Alanson, 1895-
8-4
Scribner, Charles, 1921-
8-12
Soop, Everett J., 1901-
8-9
Trapido, Harold
March 23, 1945; March 28.1945; September 12, 1945; March 14, 1946; March 21, 1946; March 22, 1946; July 26, 1947; August 1, 1947; August 22, 1947; September 26, 1947; October 27, 1947; November 12, 1947; April 23, 1948; January 6, 1949; see also 5-33; 8-17; 10-8
Twente, John W.
5-32; 8-16; 8-17; 10-8
Wagman, Frederick H.
8-20
Wilgus, A. Curtis (Alva Curtis), 1897-1981.
5-35; 9-15